Lydia Rapoport Papers, 1960-1968
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Lydia Rapoport Papers
1963-1968
Rapoport, Lydia
MS 149
1 box (1 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Professor and social worker. Articles highlight the extensive research she conducted on the topics of family intervention, mental health consultation, and short-term casework. In the course of her career, Rapoport conducted consultations, workshops, and seminars at various institutions in the U.S. and abroad. Material includes correspondence, lectures, and published and unpublished articles.
Biographical Note
Lydia Rapoport was born in 1923 in Vienna, Austria, to an intellectual Jewish family. Her family emigrated to New York City when she was a child. She graduated from Hunter College in 1942 and went on to the Smith College School for Social Work. She received her Master's in Social Work in 1944 at the age of twenty-one, making her the youngest degree recipient in the School's history.
In the course of her career, Rapoport conducted consultations, workshops, and seminars at various institutions, among them Hebrew University in Israel from 1963 to 1964, the Smith College School for Social Work in 1965, 1966 and 1967, and the University of Chicago in 1968. She served on the faculty of the University of California at Berkeley from 1956 until her death on September 6, 1971. In 1974, the Lydia Rapoport Distinguished Visiting Professorship and Lecture Series was established in her memory at the Smith College School for Social Work.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Lydia Rapoport Papers date from 1960 to 1968. Series I. Professional Activities consists of a letter to the Curator of the Sophia Smith Collection from Robert T. Apte, Rapoport's colleague at Berkeley and donor of her papers. It details certain aspects of the time Rapoport served at that university, as well as the circumstances surrounding her death. The series also includes professional correspondence, syllabi and course outlines, course evaluations, bibliographies, and transcripts of lectures. Series II. Writings features both published and unpublished articles written at the height of her career. Published journal articles highlight the extensive research Rapoport conducted on the topics of family intervention, mental health consultation, and short-term casework. Most of the unpublished articles were written in 1963 and 1964 while Rapoport taught at the Hebrew University.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into two series:
I. Professional Activities
II. Writings
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Robert Apte donated the papers of Lydia Rapoport to the Sophia Smith Collection in May 1988.
Search Terms
Smith College. School for Social Work--History--Sources; Social case work--Study and teaching--United States--History--Sources; Social work education--United States--History--Sources; Rapoport, Lydia
Additional Information
Related Material
Related material is located in the Smith College Archives.
- SERIES I. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Correspondence containing biographical information, April 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - List of professional institutes, seminars, and workshops, 1965-68 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1963-68 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Smith College School for Social Work: course outlines and bibliography, 1965-66 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - University of California, Berkeley
    - Course outlines and bibliographies, 1967-68, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Methods of Supervision," course transcript, June 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - "Descriptions of Advanced Program in Community Mental Health," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Community Mental Health Program Prospectus, June 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "A Study of Community Services for Abused Children and their Families," by Marilyn E. Miller, June 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - University of Chicago: course evaluations, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- SERIES II. WRITINGS
  - Published works
    - Journal articles
      - "In Defense of Social Work: An Analysis of Stress in the Profession," 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - "The Concept of Prevention in Social Work": article and requests for reprints, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - "The State of Crisis: Some Theoretical Considerations": article and requests for reprints, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - "Working with Families in Crisis: An ExplorationIn Preventative Intervention," 1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - "Consultation in Social Work Practice," 1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - "The Role of Supervision in Professional Education," 1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - "Mental Health Consultation," 1964 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - "Basic Concepts in Providing Services to Families" (in English and Hebrew), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - "The Clinician's Role in Respect to Mental Health," 1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - "Consultation as a Social Work Activity," 1965 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - "Advanced Education for Practice in Community Mental Health," 1967-68 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - "Crisis-Oriented Short-term Casework": article and correspondence 1966-67 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - "Creativity in Social Work," 1968 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - "Preventative Intervention Potentials in Public Child Care Centers," 1966-68 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Unpublished works
    - Articles and casework documents
      - "Final Report on Consultation to PBSSW; The Hebrew University," 1963-64 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - "Role Considerations of Psychiatric Social Work Practice," 1964 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - "Casebook of Short-Term Casework Treatment," 1964 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - "The Casework Sequence," July 1964 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - "The Nature of Student Advising in Social Work Education," 1965 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - "The Social Work Role in Family Planning," 1965 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - "The Multi-Problem Family-Who Are They?," n.d. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Book reviews and brief articles, 1963, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Transcriptions of [?], pages 118-463, unidentified and incomplete, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34-37)
    - Speech: "Social Casework: An Appraisal and an Affirmation," address given at 50th Anniversary of the Smith College School for Social Work, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 38)